Divyesh Lad

16 Overland Road, Croydon Park, Adelaide 🏫 SA 5008

0435670019

divyeshlad@protonmail.com



linkedin.com/in/divyesh-lad-abaa7188 in



Recently graduated data scientist with 10 months of experience in collecting, interpreting, and analyzing large datasets. Knowledgeable in artificial intelligence, machine learning, and big data. A highly skilled communicator, with extensive technical knowledge to serve as a trusted and valuable consultant. Ability to collaborate with all levels of internal and external developers, and project stakeholders. Interested in model building that drives long-term business growth.

Experience

Research Assistant Data Analyst

University of South Australia - C3L - Adelaide, SA

MARCH 2020 – present

Working with the Centre for Change and Complexity Lab (C3L) under the Teaching and Innovation Unit at UniSA.

- Performed ETL and presented the results in the form of an Excel pivot table to understand the behavior of students.
- · Leveraged data warehousing and visualizing capabilities in Python to compare and understand the influence of different factors on students' online engagement activity.
- Implemented linear mixed models (Imer) in R to estimate the student performance by controlling random factors of student id.
- Performed extensive post-hoc analysis to check the residual assumptions.
- Wrote python scripts to automate data merging & transformation, masking, and visualization processes.
- Built a new feature engineering approach to improve the model's overall predictive power.

Natural Language Processing Engineer

Creative Mantra

JUNE 2020 – present

Working on an online editing platform to provide an in-depth analysis of prose.

- Spearheaded the implementation of building features and creating automated reports to meet the demands of publishing professionals and discerning readers.
- Developed, evaluated, and maintained NLP modules that assisted authors in improving the manuscript by recommending cleaner dialogue, eliminating needless filler, keeping the reader engaged by finetuning pacing, and setting the emotional tone of the writing.
- Monitored and created test cases in a Python environment for different modules related to pacing, dialogue delivery, and word choice for validating data and resolving issues.

Achievement: Decreased the rate of false positives in the traditional model by ~10% following robust data cleaning and wrangling procedures.

Data Visualization Consultant

City of Adelaide NOV 2019 – DEC 2019

Worked with Adelaide council's business development department on the Smart CBD project.

- Delivered an interactive dashboard in **Power BI** for retailers to make informed decisions about the vacancy and occupancy rates of businesses in the city precinct.
- Optimized the existing design by performing rigorous data cleaning to highlight the major businesses at the precinct level.
- Integrated data from multiple data sources and maintained the integrity of the database.

Achievement: Built a POC to identify the key relationship between revenue earned and the rent paid by the businesses which in-turn helped the council to support industries with lower income and startups.

Internships

Data Science Intern

ValAI - Adelaide, SA

APRIL 2020 – present

- Created automated scripts to deploy the model in the production environment and maintain data processing workflow.
- Implemented PL-SQL queries to pull data from the PostgreSQL database to a python environment.
- Collaborated with property valuators to perform feature selection and build AVM (Automated Valuation Model) to forecast the property prices in Adelaide.
- Built an end-to-end machine learning model using tree-based algorithms to increase the model explainability from 60% to 78%.

Research Data Analytics Intern

University of South Australia - C3L - Adelaide, SA

FEBRUARY 2020 - MARCH 2020

- Identify, analyze, and interpret patterns in complex datasets to provide on-going reports.
- Managed and integrated different data sources to resolve merge issues.

Capstone Program Intern

City of Adelaide

SEP 2019 – NOV 2019

- Contextualized and summarized different data governance policies and regulations on data privacy, data accessibility, data sharing, and data quality & assurance.
- Wrote scripts in DAX & python editor in Power BI environment to clean, transform, and analyze data.
- Gained exposure to data visualization tools and the operations in agile scrum methodology.

Research and Development Intern

Ecosmob Technologies – Ahmedabad

FEB 2018 - MACRH 2018

 Suggested supervised machine learning algorithms to optimize the internal workflow of the organization.

Skills

Technical Skills: Data Mining, Data Visualization, Machine learning, Artificial Intelligence, and Natural Language Processing

Programming Language: Python, R, SQL, Java, C, C++, Bash, and Scala

Tools & Frameworks: Apache Spark, Hadoop, Hive, Impala, Apache Pig, SAS Enterprise Miner / Studio, and Git

Certifications

- Certified in MS-SQL Server data administrator practices. (LinkedIn Learning August 2020)
- Training in **Git** Essential Basics. (LinkedIn Learning June 2020)
- Acquired Excel Data Analysis skills. (LinkedIn Learning Jan 2020)
- Knowledgeable in Deep Learning: Image Recognition (LinkedIn Learning Oct 2019)
- Certification in Improving Deep Neural Networks (Coursera August 2019)
- Certification in Neural Network (Coursera July 2019)
- CCA Spark and Hadoop Developer (Cloudera March 2017)

Education

University of South Australia

Master of Data Science (6.15 out of 7)

Graduated - 12/2019

- Top 10% percentile in class.
- Volunteered to work for a non-profit organization (Birthing Kit Foundation Australia) on a data migration project.

Parul University

Bachelor of Computer Science (6.3 out of 10)

Graduated - 05/2016